<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
	<info>
		<update version="1.8">
			<file name="maarut.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Wond3rjay/dnd/refs/heads/main/races/maarut.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>	
	<element name="Maarut" type="Race" source="Jay Homebrew and Additions" id="ID_JAY_RACE_MAARUT">
		<description>
			<p>Wild at heart, wild of nature, the simian cousins of Humans, Maarut are deceptive in appearance. For people oblivious of their existence, they might appear unrestrained agents of chaos. But there is a method to their madness, often backed by a font of intelligence and or wisdom. They are fond of art, music, and revelry but also take pride in performing their responsibilities and duties. Wit, intellectualism, and wisdom draws them into conversation, but they also typically good at hiding their wariness underneath a cloak of amicability.</p>
			<h4>Nature</h4>
			<p>They serve the order and justice with loyalty, but are always a step away to unleash the chaos burning inside their core if it helps the needy. However, such dangerous devotion to altruism often leads to them poking hornet's nests in the worst way possible. But such daring and hardheaded fortitude has also led many such Maarut to perform supernatural feats. Due to such core principles and internal nature, many Maarut lean towards Chaotic Good.</p>
			<h4>Life on Maa</h4>
			<p>On Maa, the majority of Maarut reside on Jeevan continent. In the north, many Maarut often become law peacekeepers for the Mithras Empire. In Central Jeevan, Maarut have their own kingdom, Kishkisha, a vassal state of Borosh Empire, located on and around Mountain Kapimook.</p>
			<h4>MAARUT TRAITS</h4>
			<p>Your maarut character has the following traits.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Creature Type.</em></strong> You are a Humanoid.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability Score Increase.</em></strong> Increase one score by 2 and increase a different score by 1, or you increase three different scores by 1.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Size.</em></strong> You are Medium Size. Maarut generally grow up to 4 to 6.5 feet or roughly 120 cm to 200 cm</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Speed.</em></strong> Your base walking speed is 35 feet or 10.7 meters. Your base climbing speed is 25 feet or 7.6 meters.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Age.</em></strong> Maarut mature at the age of eighteen (18) years old and have a natural average lifespan of 120 years.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Alignment Recommendation.</em></strong> Maarut gravitate towards good. They have immense respect for the law until they find corruption or cannibalization of the system which may propel them to stir chaos to restore a benevolent order.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Third Appendage.</em></strong>  You have a long tail that can be nimble, strong, and sturdy. With your tail, you may:</p>
				<p><ul class="unstyled">
					<li style="margin-left:1em;text-indent:-1em;"><strong>Grab and Hurl.</strong> Pick up a blunt object (up to 10 pounds) within reach (5 ft) and then throw it as a ranged attack as a bonus action towards a target (range 30ft/60ft) to deal 1d6 bludgeoning damage on hit. Or pick up a blunt object (up to 30 pounds) within reach and make a ranged attack as an attack action at a target (range 15ft/30ft) to deal 1d10 bludgeoning damage on hit. You may use Dexterity modifier for Grab and Throw attack rolls.</li>
					<li style="margin-left:1em;text-indent:-1em;"><p><strong>Grappling Tail.</strong> As an attack action, you may use your free tail to attempt a grapple a creature, large size or smaller, that is behind you. A creature grappled by your tail stays behind your back, and thus any attack against that creature made by you must be made with disadvantage. The creature may break grapple as an action by contesting an athletics or acrobatics check against your athletics check on their turn.</p>
					<p>You may grapple another creature within range using a free hand as stated on PHB p195 while having a creature grappled by your tail.</p></li>
					<li style="margin-left:1em;text-indent:-1em;"><strong>Constrict and Trip.</strong> As an attack action, make a grapple check with your free tail against a target, large size or smaller, within melee range. If you succeed, the target falls prone and takes bludgeoning damage equals to your strength modifier. If you fail, the next attack against you gains advantage.</li>
					<li style="margin-left:1em;text-indent:-1em;"><strong>Nimble Yank.</strong> When located within 5 feet of a medium or large stationary object that your tail can wrap around, such as a pillar or tree that weighs more than you, you may use the said object to slingshot yourself up to 10 feet past it as a reaction after an attack is made against you.</li>
				</ul></p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Primal Instincts.</em></strong> You gain proficiency with two of the following skills of your choice: Athletics, Acrobatics, Stealth, and Sleight of Hand.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Underestimated Talents.</em></strong> You gain proficiency in one Musical Instrument and in one any other tool or Gaming Set.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Languages.</em></strong> You can speak, read, and write Common and two other languages of your choice.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<setters>
			<set name="names" type="masculine">Angad, Baali, Greev, Feeki, Nall, Neel, Kesari, Soon, Jabari, Baakoo</set>
			<set name="names" type="feminine">Anjana, Rooma, Sugri, Taara, Makari, Neela, Saari, Joon, Sushena, Dariyaa</set>
		</setters>
		<rules>
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Ability Score Improvement Option (Maarut)" supports="Custom Ability Score Improvement Option" />
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +2 (Maarut)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 2" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +1 (Maarut)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 1" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<grant type="Size" id="ID_SIZE_MEDIUM" />
			<stat name="innate speed" value="35" bonus="base" />
			<stat name="innate speed:climb" value="20" bonus="base" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_JAY_RACE_MAARUT_THIRD_APPENDAGE_GRAB_HURL" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_JAY_RACE_MAARUT_THIRD_APPENDAGE_GRAPPLING_TAIL" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_JAY_RACE_MAARUT_THIRD_APPENDAGE_CONSTRICT_TRIP" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_JAY_RACE_MAARUT_THIRD_APPENDAGE_QGRAB_HURL" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_JAY_RACE_MAARUT_THIRD_APPENDAGE_NIMBLE_YANK" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_JAY_RACE_MAARUT_PRIMAL_INSTINCTS" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_JAY_RACE_MAARUT_UNDERESTIMATED_TALENTS" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_COMMON" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_LANGUAGE" />
			<select type="Language" name="Customized Language" supports="Custom Race Language" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_LANGUAGE" />
			<select type="Language" name="Language, Maarut" supports="Standard||Exotic" number="2" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Third Appendage, Grab and Hurl" type="Racial Trait" source="Jay Homebrew and Additions" id="ID_JAY_RACE_MAARUT_THIRD_APPENDAGE_GRAB_HURL">
		<description>
			<p>You have a long tail that can be nimble, strong, and sturdy. With your tail, you may:</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Action">
			<description> You may pick up a blunt object (up to 30 pounds) within reach and make a ranged attack with your tail as an attack action at a target (range 15ft/30ft) to deal 1d10 bludgeoning damage on hit. You may use Dexterity modifier for Grab and Throw attack rolls.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Third Appendage, Grappling Tail" type="Racial Trait" source="Jay Homebrew and Additions" id="ID_JAY_RACE_MAARUT_THIRD_APPENDAGE_GRAPPLING_TAIL">
		<description>
			<p>You have a long tail that can be nimble, strong, and sturdy. With your tail, you may:</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Action">
			<description> As an attack action, you may use your free tail to attempt a grapple a creature, large size or smaller, that is behind you. A creature grappled by your tail stays behind your back, and thus any attack against that creature made by you must be made with disadvantage. The creature may break grapple as an action by contesting an athletics or acrobatics check against your athletics check on their turn. You may grapple another creature within range using a free hand as stated on PHB p195 while having a creature grappled by your tail.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Third Appendage, Constrict and Trip" type="Racial Trait" source="Jay Homebrew and Additions" id="ID_JAY_RACE_MAARUT_THIRD_APPENDAGE_CONSTRICT_TRIP">
		<description>
			<p>You have a long tail that can be nimble, strong, and sturdy. With your tail, you may:</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Action">
			<description> As an attack action, make a grapple check with your free tail against a target, large size or smaller, within melee range. If you succeed, the target falls prone and takes bludgeoning damage equals to your strength modifier. If you fail, the next attack against you gains advantage.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Third Appendage, Quick Grab and Hurl" type="Racial Trait" source="Jay Homebrew and Additions" id="ID_JAY_RACE_MAARUT_THIRD_APPENDAGE_QGRAB_HURL">
		<description>
			<p>You have a long tail that can be nimble, strong, and sturdy. With your tail, you may:</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Bonus Action">
			<description> You may pick up a blunt object (up to 10 pounds) within reach and make a ranged attack with your tail as a bonus action at a target (range 30ft/60ft) to deal 1d6 bludgeoning damage on hit. You may use Dexterity modifier for Grab and Throw attack rolls.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Third Appendage, Nimble Yank" type="Racial Trait" source="Jay Homebrew and Additions" id="ID_JAY_RACE_MAARUT_THIRD_APPENDAGE_NIMBLE_YANK">
		<description>
			<p>You have a long tail that can be nimble, strong, and sturdy. With your tail, you may:</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Reaction">
			<description> When located within 5 feet of a medium or large stationary object that your tail can wrap around, such as a pillar or tree that weighs more than you, you may use the said object to slingshot yourself up to 10 feet past it as a reaction after an attack is made against you.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Primal Instincts" type="Racial Trait" source="Jay Homebrew and Additions" id="ID_JAY_RACE_MAARUT_PRIMAL_INSTINCTS">
		<description>
			<p>You gain proficiency with two of the following skills of your choice: Athletics, Acrobatics, Stealth, or Sleight of Hand.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>You gain proficiency with two of the following skills of your choice: Athletics, Acrobatics, Stealth, or Sleight of Hand.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<select type="Proficiency" name="Skill Proficiency, Primal Instincts" supports="ID_PROFICIENCY_SKILL_ATHLETICS|ID_PROFICIENCY_SKILL_ACROBATICS|ID_PROFICIENCY_SKILL_STEALTH|ID_PROFICIENCY_SKILL_SLEIGHTOFHAND" number="2" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_PROFICIENCY" />
			<select type="Proficiency" name="Customized Skill Proficiency, Primal Instincts"  number="2" supports="Skill" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_PROFICIENCY" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Underestimated Talents" type="Racial Trait" source="Jay Homebrew and Additions" id="ID_JAY_RACE_MAARUT_UNDERESTIMATED_TALENTS">
		<description>
			<p>You gain proficiency in one Musical Instrument and in one any other tool or Gaming Set.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>You gain proficiency in one Musical Instrument and in one any other tool or Gaming Set.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<select type="Proficiency" name="Mustical Instrument or Gaming Set, Maarut" supports="Musical Instrument||Gaming Set" />
		</rules>
	</element>	
</elements>