<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
  <info>
        <update version="1.0.0">
      <file name="2024-spells.xml" url="/spells/2024-spells.xml"/>
    </update>
  </info>

  <element name="Arcane Vigor" type="Spell" source="WOTC" id="ID_2024_SPELL_ARCANE_VIGOR">
    <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You tap into your life force to heal yourself. Roll one or two of your unexpended Hit Point Dice, and regain a number of Hit Points equal to the roll's total plus your spellcasting ability modifier. Those dice are then expended.</p>
	  <p><b>Using a Higher-Level Spell Slot.</b> The number of unexpended Hit Dice you can roll increases by one for each spell slot level above 2.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="level">2</set>
      <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 bonus action</set>
      <set name="duration">instantaneous</set>
      <set name="range">Self</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
	  <set name="materialComponent"/>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Befuddlement" type="Spell" source="WOTC" id="ID_2024_SPELL_BEFUDDLEMENT">
    <supports>Bard, Druid, Warlock, Wizard, Spell Saving Throw</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You blast the mind of a creature that you can see within range. The target makes an Intelligence saving throw.</p>
		<p>On a failed save, the target takes 10d12 Psychic damage and can't cast spells or take the Magic action. At the end of every 30 days, the target repeats the save, ending the effect on a success. The effect can also be ended by the Greater Restoration, Heal, or Wish spell.</p>
		<p>On a successful save, the target takes half as much damage only.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="level">8</set>
      <set name="school">Enchantment</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">instantaneous</set>
      <set name="range">150 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
	  <set name="materialComponent">a key ring with no keys</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Drawmij’s Instant Summons" type="Spell" source="WOTC" id="ID_2024_SPELL_INSTANT_SUMMON">
    <supports>Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You touch the sapphire used in the casting and an object weighing 10 pounds or less whose longest dimension is 6 feet or less. The spell leaves an Invisible mark on that object and invisibly inscribes the object's name on the sapphire. Each time you cast this spell, you must use a different sapphire.</p>
	  <p>Thereafter, you can take a Magic action to speak the object's name and crush the sapphire. The object instantly appears in your hand regardless of physical or planar distances, and the spell ends.</p>
	  <p>If another creature is holding or carrying the object, crushing the sapphire doesn't transport it, but instead you learn who that creature is and where that creature is currently located.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="level">6</set>
      <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 minute</set>
      <set name="duration">until dispelled</set>
      <set name="range">touch</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
	  <set name="materialComponent">a sapphire worth 1,000+ GP</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">true</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Elementalism" type="Spell" source="WOTC" id="ID_2024_SPELL_ELEMENTALISM">
    <supports> Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You exert control over the elements, creating one of the following effects within range.</p>
	  <p><b>Beckon Air.</b> You create a breeze strong enough to ripple cloth, stir dust, rustle leaves, and close open doors and shutters, all in a 5-foot Cube. Doors and shutters being held open by someone or something aren't affected.</p>
	  <p><b>Beckon Earth.</b> You create a thin shroud of dust or sand that covers surfaces in a 5-foot-square area, or you cause a single word to appear in your handwriting in a patch of dirt or sand.<p><b>Beckon Fire.</b> You create a thin cloud of harmless embers and colored, scented smoke in a 5-foot Cube. You choose the color and scent, and the embers can light candles, torches, or lamps in that area. The smoke's scent lingers for 1 minute.</p>
	  <p><b>Beckon Water.</b> You create a spray of cool mist that lightly dampens creatures and objects in a 5-foot Cube. Alternatively, you create 1 cup of clean water either in an open container or on a surface, and the water evaporates in 1 minute.</p>
	  <p><b>Sculpt Element.</b> You cause dirt, sand, fire, smoke, mist, or water that can fit in a 1-foot Cube to assume a crude shape (such as that of a creature) for 1 hour.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="level">0</set>
      <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">instantaneous</set>
      <set name="range">30 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
	  <set name="materialComponent"/>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Fount of Moonlight" type="Spell" source="WOTC" id="ID_2024_SPELL_FOUNT_OF_MOONLIGHT">
    <supports>Bard, Druid, Spell Saving Throw</supports>
    <description>
      <p>A cool light wreathes your body for the duration, emitting Bright Light in a 20-foot radius and Dim Light for an additional 20 feet.</p>
	  <p>Until the spell ends, you have Resistance to Radiant damage, and your melee attacks deal an extra 2d6 Radiant damage on a hit.</p>
	  <p>In addition, immediately after you take damage from a creature you can see within 60 feet of yourself, you can take a Reaction to force the creature to make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, the creature has the Blinded condition until the end of your next turn.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="level">4</set>
      <set name="school">Evocation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">up to 10 minutes</set>
      <set name="range">self</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
	  <set name="materialComponent"/>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Jallarzi's Storm of Radiance" type="Spell" source="WOTC" id="ID_2024_SPELL_STORM_OF_RADIANCE">
    <supports>Warlock, Wizard, Spell Saving Throw</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You unleash a storm of flashing light and raging thunder in a 10-foot-radius, 40-foot-high Cylinder centered on a point you can see within range. While in this area, creatures have the Blinded and Deafened conditions, and they can't cast spells with a Verbal component.</p>
	  <p>When the storm appears, each creature in it makes a Constitution saving throw, taking 2d10 Radiant damage and 2d10 Thunder damage on a failed save or half as much damage on a successful one. A creature also makes this save when it enters the spell's area for the first time on a turn or ends its turn there. A creature makes this save only once per turn.</p>
	  <p><b>Using a Higher-Level Spell Slot.</b> The Radiant and Thunder damage increase by 1d10 for each spell slot level above 5.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="level">5</set>
      <set name="school">Evocation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">up to 1 minutes</set>
      <set name="range">120 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
	  <set name="materialComponent">a pinch of phosphorus</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Power Word Fortify" type="Spell" source="WOTC" id="ID_2024_SPELL_POWER_WORD_FORTIFY">
    <supports>Bard, Cleric</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You fortify up to six creatures you can see within range. The spell bestows 120 Temporary Hit Points, which you divide among the spell's recipients.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="level">7</set>
      <set name="school">Enchantment</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">instantaneous</set>
      <set name="range">60 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
	  <set name="materialComponent"/>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Shining Smite" type="Spell" source="WOTC" id="ID_2024_SPELL_SHINING_SMITE">
    <supports>Paladin</supports>
    <description>
      <p>The target hit by the strike takes an extra 2d6 Radiant damage from the attack. Until the spell ends, the target sheds Bright Light in a 5-foot radius, attack rolls against it have Advantage, and it can't benefit from the Invisible condition.</p>
	  <p><b>Using a Higher-Level Spell Slot.</b> The damage increases by 1d6 for each spell slot level above 2.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="level">2</set>
      <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
      <set name="time">1 bonus action, which you take immediately after hitting a creature with a Melee weapon or an Unarmed Strike</set>
      <set name="duration">up to 1 minute</set>
      <set name="range">self</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
	  <set name="materialComponent"/>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Sorcerous Burst" type="Spell" source="WOTC" id="ID_2024_SPELL_SORCEROUS_BURST">
    <supports>Sorcerer</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You cast sorcerous energy at one creature or object within range. Make a ranged attack roll against the target. On a hit, the target takes 1d8 damage of a type you choose: Acid, Cold, Fire, Lightning, Poison, Psychic, or Thunder.</p>
	  <p>If you roll an 8 on a d8 for this spell, you can roll another d8, and add it to the damage. When you cast this spell, the maximum number of these d8s you can add to the spell's damage equals your spellcasting ability modifier.</p>
	  <p><b>Cantrip Upgrade.</b> The damage increases by 1d8 when you reach levels 5 (2d8), 11 (3d8), and 17 (4d8).</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="level">0</set>
      <set name="school">Evocation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">instantaneous</set>
      <set name="range">120 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
	  <set name="materialComponent"/>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Starry Wisp" type="Spell" source="WOTC" id="ID_2024_SPELL_STARRY_WISP">
    <supports>Bard, Druid</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You launch a mote of light at one creature or object within range. Make a ranged spell attack against the target. On a hit, the target takes 1d8 Radiant damage, and until the end of your next turn, it emits Dim Light in a 10-foot radius and can't benefit from the Invisible condition.</p>
	  <p><b>Cantrip Upgrade.</b> The damage increases by 1d8 when you reach levels 5 (2d8), 11 (3d8), and 17 (4d8).</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="level">0</set>
      <set name="school">Evocation</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">instantaneous</set>
      <set name="range">60 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
	  <set name="materialComponent"/>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Tasha's Bubbling Cauldron" type="Spell" source="WOTC" id="ID_2024_BUBBLING_CAULDRON">
    <supports>Warlock, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You conjure a claw-footed cauldron filled with bubbling liquid. The cauldron appears in an unoccupied space on the ground within 5 feet of you and lasts for the duration. The cauldron can't be moved and disappears when the spell ends, along with the bubbling liquid inside it.</p>
	  <p>The liquid in the cauldron duplicates the properties of a Common or an Uncommon potion of your choice (such as a Potion of Healing). As a Bonus Action, you or an ally can reach into the cauldron and withdraw one potion of that kind. The potion is contained in a vial that disappears when the potion is consumed. The cauldron can produce a number of these potions equal to your spellcasting ability modifier (minimum 1). When the last of these potions is withdrawn from the cauldron, the cauldron disappears, and the spell ends.</p>
	  <p>Potions obtained from the cauldron that aren't consumed disappear when you cast this spell again.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="level">6</set>
      <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">10 minutes</set>
      <set name="range">60 feet</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
	  <set name="materialComponent">a gilded ladle worth 500 + GP</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
  <element name="Yolande's Regal Presence" type="Spell" source="WOTC" id="ID_2024_REGAL_PRESENCE">
    <supports>Bard, Wizard</supports>
    <description>
      <p>You surround yourself with unearthly majesty in a 10-foot Emanation. Whenever the Emanation enters the space of a creature you can see and whenever a creature you can see enters the Emanation or ends its turn there, you can force that creature to make a Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the target takes 4d6 Psychic damage and has the Prone condition, and you can push it up to 10 feet away. On a successful save, the target takes half as much damage only. A creature makes this save only once per turn.</p>
    </description>
    <setters>
      <set name="level">5</set>
      <set name="school">Enchantment</set>
      <set name="time">1 action</set>
      <set name="duration">up to 1 minutes</set>
      <set name="range">self</set>
      <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
      <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
	  <set name="materialComponent">a miniature tiara</set>
      <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
      <set name="isRitual">false</set>
    </setters>
  </element>
</elements>